<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antidotum Culmerianum: or, Animadversions upon a late pamphlet, entituled, Cathedrall newes from Canterbury, &amp;c. by Richard Culmer, who is here (according to his friends desire, and his own desert) set forth in his colours.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E279_13</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860835</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860835</idno>
            <idno type="VID">130524</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75475)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 130524)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 46:E279[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antidotum Culmerianum: or, Animadversions upon a late pamphlet, entituled, Cathedrall newes from Canterbury, &amp;c. by Richard Culmer, who is here (according to his friends desire, and his own desert) set forth in his colours.</title>
                  <author>Culmer, Richard, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hall.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644 [i.e. 1645?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"This was undoubtedly written in the autumn of 1644 but was received by Thomason on April 30, 1645: so either it was long in reaching Thomason, or, as is more probable, there was delay in printing and publishing the book, and the "1644" on the title page was never altered"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>"A copie of the information presented to the Councell-table by Richard Culmer, against M. E.B.", E3v-E4r.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; final leaf torn, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Culmer, Richard, d. 1662. --  Cathedrall newes from Canterbury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:130524:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Antidotum Culmerianum: OR, ANIMADVERSIONS UPON A late Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>Cathedrall Newes from Canterbury,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> RICHARD CULMER, Who is here (according to his friends deſire, and his own deſert) ſet forth in his colours.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 63.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The mouth of them that ſpeak lies ſhall be ſtopped.</p>
            </q>
            <q>Iſtie theſaurus ſtultis in lingua poſitus eſt, ut maledicant melioribus.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gildas Eccleſiaſtic. Ordin. Corrept.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Britannia habet Sacerdotes, ſed nonnullos inſipientes; quampluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos Miniſtros, ſed multos impudentes: —ſaepius detrahen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; rarò vera dicentes: veritatem pro inimico odientes, &amp; mendaciis ac ſi chariſſimis fratribus faventes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hall.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:130524:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:130524:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>WAlking London-ſtreets, which eccho with nothing more of late, then <hi>Newes,</hi> and <hi>Newes-books:</hi>
               <q>(Eme Liſippe nevos totâ canit urbe libellos)</q> And hearing one, among the reſt of that upſtart Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (of <hi>Newes-mongers</hi>) proclaime <hi>Cathedrall Newes from Canterbury,</hi> a place whereunto I have formerly had ſome relation; and in my progreſſe a little further, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very ſame Newes objected to common view on ſome Stationers ſtalls, reeking hot, as new as day, being by the midwifery of the Preſſe newly brought into the world, for the arguments ſake, I could not but turn pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer, and beſtow a ſmall piece of ſilver on it, reſolving after I had peruſed it my ſelf, to communicate it unto one or other of mine old acquaintance upon the place. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring therefore to my chamber, I preſently fell to the fetching out my penny-worths: and, though I found the <hi>Canterbury-tale</hi> ſomwhat long, yet the length of it ſo ſweetened with gallant palate-pleaſing mixtures and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties, ſavouring as well of profit as delight, the prime procurers of an authours praiſe,
<q>(Omne tulit punctum qui miſcuit utile dulci)</q> and ſet off with Rhetoricall flowers, and the quinteſſence of inticing language, I would not, I could not leave it, after I had once begun, untill a through peruſall. And how much the rather, for the noble and famous Authors ſake; a man whoſe ſweetneſſe and meekneſſe of temper, and Dove-like conditions, do notably anſwer to that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular antipathy to the breed of Snakes and Serpents,<note place="margin">See <hi>Lambard.</hi> perambul. of <hi>Kent,</hi> in <hi>Tanet.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>Solinus</hi> an old Hiſtorian, aſcribed to his native ſoile, (the Iſle of <hi>Thanet:</hi>) being indeed a man (as I have
<pb facs="tcp:130524:3"/>heard, and partly know) of great gravity, ſingular mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and other rare gifts, both naturall and acquired: whereof what further evidence needs any man expect, then the preſent elaborate piece, the book in hand. This indeed is my opinion; wherein I think I am ſo right, ſo modeſt in my Encomiaſtick of the worthy Authour, as I ſhall not need to doubt of any mans concurrence in opinion with me. And being taken with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the Authours leaving the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> to follow the <hi>Preſſe;</hi> in a humour I reſolved to leave my old trade (of ſtreet-walking) and go to try another while how I could play the <hi>Mercury,</hi> and write a piece of Newes. Furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therefore with materialls from <hi>Thanet,</hi> from the <hi>Free-Schoole</hi> at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> from <hi>Magdalen-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> from <hi>Goodneſtone</hi> in <hi>Eaſt-Kent,</hi> from <hi>Herbaldowne</hi> and elſwhere, I put them in Rank and File, and marſhal'd them as well as I could in the following ſheets; how handſomely I feare, it being my firſt Eſſay of this kind, the firſt time I ever offered at the <hi>Mercury.</hi> Some candor may incourage the new beginner to ſtudie your requitall with better fruits hereafter. In the meane time (good Reader, to be ſerious with thee) expect not here any med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with <hi>State-matters,</hi> any cenſuring of Superiours, any reflexion upon the higher Powers: no, the <hi>Newes</hi> and the <hi>Newes-monger</hi> (and ſome of his mates) are the ſole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this diſcourſe, and that only (as thou haſt it in the <hi>Title</hi>) for an antidote againſt ſuch groſſe and notorious ſlanders upon his brethren, as his malicious pen, under the notion of <hi>Newes,</hi> endeavours to obtrude upon credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous vulgar Readers in theſe cenſorious times; whileſt, for want of a mirrour to repreſent unto them the Accuſer himſelfe in his own likeneſſe, what might ſet a due value and a right eſtimate upon his cenſures of other men, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together wanting. Thus advertiſed, I bid thee <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:130524:3"/>
            <head>Antidotum Culmerianum: OR, Animadverſions upon a late Pamphlet, ENTITULED, <hi>Cathedrall Newes from Canterburie:</hi> BY RICHARD CULMER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O begin with the <hi>Title, Cathedrall Newes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Newes.</note> What a falſe Signe is here hung out? What an <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> hath this Scribler lighted, both to his Patrons and Reader? <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Newes?</hi> Why how now friend? What out as ſoone as in? Out at the very firſt ſtep? Stumble at the threſhold? <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Newes,</hi> quoth he? Nothing leſſe man. Doth not the whole Kingdome ring of the ſpoile of many of its goodlieſt Cathedralls, become <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyria,</hi> (objects of <hi>Martyrdome</hi>) by the fury and malice of ſuch deſperate wild Reformers as you and: your fellowes, ſince theſe armes taken up, as at <hi>Wincheſter, Lincolne, Lichfield, Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">— En quò diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia Templa Perdaxit niti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da—</note> &amp;c. and is the ſerving the <hi>Canterburian Cathedrall</hi> in the like kind, or worſe, <hi>Cathedrall Newes</hi> now? Away, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken man! away with your ſtale newes, ſtinking ſtale indeed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:130524:4"/>if ever any, in the noſtrils both of God and all good men, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wretch! abuſe Gods Houſe, deface his Temple, and then vaunt, and boaſt, and bragg on't? glorie in your ſhame? triumph in your turpitude? make Ballads of it? add impudence to your ſacriledge? <hi>Proh ſcelus infandum!</hi> A <hi>peccavi</hi> (one would think) a <hi>Miſerere mei,</hi> an humble confeſſion, accompanied with an hearty contrition would have better become you.</p>
            <p>But ſtay,<note place="margin">From whence</note> what's next? <hi>From Canterbury, Cathedrall Newes from Canterbury.</hi> To ſee: what out again? Fie, blunderer, fie! what another ſtumble? miſtaken ſtill? Call you this ſtory (of yours) of that Cathedrals courſe uſage, <hi>Newes?</hi> No ſuch matter, friend: 'tis but the ſecond part of ſuch <hi>Reformation-Newes</hi> from thence. The Reformation I wis, of that Cathedrall by ſome friends of yours, begun (you know, and I feare the ſtreets of <hi>Aſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ring of it ere this time, how much more every corner of the Kingdome:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Pask</hi> to the Earl of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, <hi>1642.</hi>
               </note>) well neere two years ſince, the true ſtory whereof recorded in a Letter written to a noble Lord from a worthy member of that Society (however ſcorn'd and ſlander'd by your paultrie pen, whilſt you are not worthy to wipe his ſhooes) po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity cannot read, without a due mixture of wonderment, and deteſtation; deteſting the action, whileſt they wonder not ſo much (perhaps) at the actors as at the age they liv'd in, crying out with the Poet, <hi>O tempora! O mores!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well,<note place="margin">What.</note> but the <hi>Canterburian Cathedrall</hi> (for ſo he adds) <hi>is in an Abbey-like, corrupt, and rotten condition</hi> &amp;c. What meane you, friend? the materiall ſtructure, the Fabrick? If ſo, 'tis true e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Abbeyes indeed ever ſince their deſerved demolition and downfall, have been in ſuch a <hi>corrupt and rotten condition,</hi> a negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted prey to winds and weather; and to the like doth that Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall tend apace, thanks to you and your fellowes <hi>Orderly Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> whereby it is expoſed to the injurie of all weathers, by removing its wonted glazen ſhelter of a ſtrange thickneſſe, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as, what with the <hi>Raine</hi> ſomtimes, with <hi>Snow</hi> another while, getting in at the broken windowes in great abundance, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and rottenneſſe have begun to ſeize on the walls. And for the Floore, in what a ſtrange uncouth pickle it was, all the Church<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>warme and well-ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sermon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</hi> it ſelfe (pag. <hi>2.</hi>) not excepted.</note> over, with the great Snow the laſt winter, and both before and ſince with the raine, is too well knowne (I wiſh it were not) both to ſtrangers and domeſticks: the ſtory whereof (of that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:130524:4"/>
               <hi>Orderly Reformation,</hi> I meane) is not now to write, though this be no time for truth, and true ſtories of this kind to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>Veritas odium parit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we miſtake the man. This is no part of his meaning.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Strange news,</hi> and why.</note> 'Tis the <hi>Politicall</hi> not the <hi>materiall</hi> condition of the Cathedrall he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, the <hi>Conſtitution of the Society</hi> there. And is that your meaning, friend? Why then you tell us newes indeed, and very ſtrange newes too; ſuch as your fardell of arguments, <hi>à ſolis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularibus, à merè perſonalibus,</hi> ſhall never beare you out in. What? do you think to argue down a Society, a Corporation. a Colledge, a Company, from the perſonall faults, abuſes, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, failings of ſome one or more particular members, and ſome of them, if true, not their own neither, but their wives, or their ſervants? What Society then of any kind ſhall ever ſtand? What Function not miſcarrie? Shall we have no more Miniſters, no more Magiſtrates, becauſe of each ſort ſome have beene Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents? Doughty Logick! Or, to argue <hi>ad hominem:</hi> There have been rakehellie boyes ſomtimes at the <hi>Canterburian</hi> Free-Schoole, and ſuch, that, for an offence of an high nature, being threatned with due correction, have taken Sanctuary in a<note n="*" place="margin">A ſhrewd ſigne of a bad cauſe; for <hi>Veritas non quaerit angu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>os.</hi>
               </note> Bench-hole, &amp;c. The ſame, or ſome other, when afterwards tranſlated to the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie, have played as bad or worſe pranks there, ſuch indeed as have coſt their authors an expulſion; doth it follow hence (good <hi>Richard</hi>) by any good conſequence in Logick, that either the Schoole or Vniverſity muſt down for this?</p>
            <p>But to the <hi>Newes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stranger yet.</note> 
               <hi>the corrupt conſtitution of the Canterburian Cathedrall.</hi> What ſtrange newes is here? This verily is <hi>novum &amp; inauditum.</hi> No ſober, no well-adviſed Proteſtant, before theſe times, ever ſaid it. Paſſe you ſhall, for me, for the firſt that ever brought ſuch tidings to the eares of any true ſonne of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation</hi> of that, and the like places, by <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. In former time indeed it might, it did deſerve the terme, and therefore in an happy houre the hand of providence ſent a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, changing it from (what you call it) a <hi>neſt of idolatrous, proud, lazie, covetous Monks,</hi> into a Colledge of <hi>learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Labourers in Gods Harveſt,</hi> yeelding, from time to time, ſuch numbers of worthy Divines, and of excellent parts, ſome in preaching, others in writing, Champions of ſuch value, both (thoſe with the tongue, theſe with the pen) againſt thoſe <hi>Samſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:130524:5"/>Foxes</hi> (<hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Amſterdam</hi>) as are, or ought to be, of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious memory in all the Churches of the Saints, both at home and abroad. Be ingenuous, friend, if you can, and tell me in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſadneſſe,<note place="margin">The <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Cathedrall fruitfull of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous men.</note> what thinke you of that bleſſed Martyr <hi>Ridley,</hi> your own terme, and he deſerves it) of M. <hi>Beacon,</hi> D. <hi>Bale,</hi> D. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> D. <hi>Saravia,</hi> M. <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi> D. <hi>Boys,</hi> D. <hi>Clerke,</hi> M. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> to ſay nothing of <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> the famous French Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and others haply as deſerving of the moderne Society? Theſe and many more ſuch like, are knowne (one and all) to have been in their times ſucceſſors of thoſe unworthy Monks in this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cathedrall: but can you in cold blood, put on that more then brazen impudence, as to averre their imitation of them in practice at the ſame inſtant too when your ſelfe (a <hi>burning</hi> and <hi>ſhining</hi> light) are in election to be of the Society? you may if you pleaſe; nay what do you leſſe? when in plaine termes you tell us, that theſe <hi>prelaticall ſucceſſors of the idolatrous, proud, lazy, covetous Monks, as they ſucceded them in place, ſo they followed them in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice:</hi> and in a ſcurrilous, ſcandalous, baſe character, call the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety (the Cathedrall Corporation,) <hi>A neſt of Non-Reſidents; an Epicurean Colledge of riot and voluptuouſneſſe; a Schoole for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement in Religion, but a ſcourge upon the life and practice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; A refuge for ſuperſtition, but the bane of true piety; The ſhame of the Clergy, and the ſcorne of the Laity:</hi> with many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of that prodigious nature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4, 13, 16, 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> both in your <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall other parts of your Pamphlet, ſuch as <hi>Lucian</hi> himſelfe would ſcarcely own. Hence let the indifferent Reader judge, and tell me, if we are not like to have a goodly ſuperſtructure, a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtory, when the foundation is laid in <hi>Lies,</hi> in <hi>Slanders;</hi> of ſuch a latitude, of ſuch an influence and reflexion. What others may conceive of it I know not, but I am perſwaded that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, the Jeſuits, with the whole rabble of Sectaries, will make great advantage of it againſt us, not knowing what better ſport to wiſh for, then to ſee us ſpit venome, caſt dirt in the faces of their greateſt Antagoniſts, and our chiefeſt Champions, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots and the Horſmen of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the great and glorious Aſſertors of the <hi>True Reformed Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which followes in the <hi>Title,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Miraculous Newes.</note> though not of ſo great concernment, yet is more ſtrange ſtill; <hi>The Archbiſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buries Paſſing-bell rung miraculouſly in that Cathedrall.</hi> Here I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:130524:5"/>would aske him; if he have this <hi>by his owne obſervation,</hi> or by (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) <hi>information.</hi> It ſeems from neither: for ſaving here only in the Title, we heare nothing at all of it in the whole enſuing diſcourſe. And here obſerve we a fallacy of his:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A</hi> Fallacy.</note> 
               <hi>I have the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Hiſtory</hi> (quoth he, in his Epiſtle) <hi>for the moſt part of mine own obſervation, and I have been punctuall</hi> (ſee here the Maſter-he of all) <hi>in examining the truth of what I have by information:</hi> but he placeth this paſſage, this news (of the <hi>Paſſing-bell</hi>) in the Front, before the Epiſtle, and ſo will avoid an ingagement to make it good ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, namely, by <hi>Obſervation of his owne,</hi> or <hi>Information from others.</hi> And conſequently, what have we more then his bare word for it? <hi>Ipſe dixit.</hi> And this no doubt, (out of an over-wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning magiſteriall confidence given to the Tribe, priding themſelves in a conceit of their arrivall of that height of credit in the world, that all they ſay ſhall <hi>eo ipſo</hi> be belieft) he thought would be ſufficient; expecting (it ſeems) ſuch a beliefe here, as (out of an implicite faith) is uſually afforded of the ſuperſtitious Lay-Prieſt, eſpecially the Spaniard, to what his <hi>Father-Confeſſor</hi> avoucheth for truth, Well, whileſt he expects what he pleaſeth, ſay (Reader) is not there more Gate then City? more of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe then performance? What, friend! promiſe a miracle in the Title, and prove it a lying wonder, or a wondrous lie, by a ſilent paſſing it over in the worke it ſelfe? Bad wine ſurely, where there is ſo much buſh.</p>
            <p>But from the <hi>Title,</hi> to the <hi>Author,</hi> the Hiſtorian;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Newes-monger.</note> and who's that now? Why, no <hi>Anonymus,</hi> no nameleſſe Libeller, no cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per into a Bench-hole, as one of his name once was, whence he was ferretted out at laſt, <hi>tanquam acusè ſpeluncâ,</hi> and fetch'd downe on his knees with a <hi>Miſerere mei Domine!</hi> you have his name, and with it his Title, degree, and place of abode in words at length, and not in figures: 'tis (Sir Reverence) <hi>Richard Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Miniſter of Gods word, dwelling in Canterbury; heretofore of Magdalen Colledge in Cambridge, Maſter of Arts.</hi> And what is <hi>Dick Culmer</hi> turn'd <hi>Mercury</hi> now? <hi>Mercurius Cathedralis? Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius Antipraelaticus?</hi> 'twas wont to be ſaid: <hi>Ex omni ligno non ſit Mercurius.</hi> As for <hi>Dick Culmer,</hi> he is well knowne in thoſe parts he ſpeaks of for a ſturdy, ſtout, rugged K—a man of his hands, and an able trencher-man beſides, in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> famous for foot-ball and ſwimming:<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Otherwiſe infamous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough:</hi> Qualis Gramaticus, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Academicus, ſemper idem, <hi>no</hi> verſipellis.</note> but who ever thought him cut
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:130524:6"/>out for a <hi>Mercury</hi> before? as being for thoſe abilities he hath, <hi>Marti aptior quam Mercurio,</hi> fitter for to ſerve <hi>Mars</hi> then the <hi>Muſes, &amp; Harae quam Arae,</hi> the <hi>Hogs</hi> then the <hi>Gods,</hi> better at fighting then inditing. But this is not his firſt eſſay at the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury:</hi> if you would know when he firſt ſat up, it was about Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas laſt, when he tooke and ſent up in writing to a brother <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> (as he is communicative) a learned Legend (for the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as full of Lies as his) of the tryall and execution of a notable Malefactor and Countryman and name-ſake, Doct. <hi>Dick:</hi> a faire beginning was it not? to date his firſt eſſayes from the Gallows. But ſee the mans popular itch? <hi>O, pulchrum eſt digito monſtrari &amp; dicier hic eſt.</hi> The Gallowes, and a poore baſe fellon ſhall bee his theam, rather then faile of publicke notice. <hi>A Jove,</hi> no; <hi>A cruce principium,</hi> 'tis with him, and much good doo't thee <hi>Dick,</hi> proceed and proſper.</p>
            <q>Alpha tuum quale eſt Omega ſit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tuum.</q>
            <p>Leaving his name,<note place="margin">His-Colledge, and demeanor there.</note> proceed we to his title: <hi>heretofore of Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen Colledge,</hi> &amp;c. Since hs is pleaſed to provoke me with the mention of his Colledge, I cannot chooſe but minde him, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Reader with a ſtory of one of his name, ſometime of that Colledge: the ſame that borrowed (as you heard erewhile) in a bench-hole, thence called to this day, <hi>Culmeri Latibulum;</hi> the ſame that at another time let himſelf down <hi>Tanet</hi> cliffes by a rope faſtened about his fathers Cowes hornes feeding by the place, to ſeek for Dawes neſts (an adventure that hath hardened him ever ſince againſt all feare of harme by the rope:) 'twas (they ſay) a red hair'd, freckle fac'd fellow, <hi>Judas</hi> nown com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, but no matter for that, <hi>caeteris imparibus:</hi> we uſe indeed to ſay that <hi>Vultus indicat animum,</hi> the index of the minde is the maws countenance, but we will anſwer that with a <hi>Froute nulla fides,</hi> 'tis uncertaine aime that is taken by the countenance, the fureſt is the converſation. But to my Story: This Collegian getting him a bag (<hi>Iudas</hi> bare the bag) for the mending his commons with boyl'd, butter'd wheat, made it his common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice about harveſt time to plunder for wheat in ſome neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fields. The owner obſerving day after day that his corne was ſtolne, but ignorant how or by whom, watch'd it one day, and tooke the thiefe <hi>damage feaſant;</hi> but let him firſt fill his bag, and then dogging him home to his burrow, the Colledge,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:130524:6"/>made his complaint of him to his Maſter, who by the notoriety of the fact finding him guilty, had him forth with into the Butte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, gat rods ready for his correction, lock'd the doore to them to prevent his eſcape, ſo that in liklihood here was no way but one with poore <hi>Dick,</hi> to pot he muſt; and yet he muſt not, at leaſt he will not, if all the deſperate wit he can ſummon up will ſave him. Inſt then as he ſhould goe too't,<note place="margin">Scelue ſcelerae tulum.</note> he breaks looſe from the Maſter and Butler both, gets him to the barrells, whereof there were divers then abroach, pulls out the ſpickets one after another, and whiles the Maſter and Butler, for ſaving the beere, buſily beſtirr'd themſelves to ſtop theſe leaks, the key unhapily being left ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the buttery doore, the fellow turnes it, and ſo eſcaped out of the buttery and Colledge both, whither (as ſome ſay) he never returned more, being immediatly, according to his juſt demerit, ſhamefully expelled. And (if our <hi>Richard</hi> be the man) whatever pride he may take in challenging that Colledge for his nurſe, or that Univerſity for his mother, neither of them doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe can reap much comfort or credit by acknowledging him for their ſon.</p>
            <p>My reaſons, if you aske them, beſides what are premiſed, you may collect from the following character and deſcription of the man,<note place="margin">His vertves.</note> reſulting from a poſie of ſome of thoſe rare vertues where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is accompliſhed, by which he is knowne at home, and for which he deſerves to be no leſſe famous abroad then that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table paire of his predeceſſors <hi>Bale</hi> and <hi>Martin,</hi> (the one a ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prieſt in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſeconds dayes, the other a ſcurrilous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi>) or any other enemy of Imparity in Church or State, ever were in former times. Herein you may expect me, and be ſure (to the beſt of my intelligence) ſhall find me, as farre from ſlander, as himſelfe from truth in moſt of the indigeſted ſtories he relates in that confuſed Chaos of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curian Eſſay.</p>
            <p>The marks of the beaſt are theſe:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Refractorineſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Impudence.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Covetouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Clamourouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnaturalneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Maliciouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. <hi>Doltiſhneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9. <hi>Lying.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And under theſe heads, as you ſhall have the mans life, (which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:130524:7"/>'twere pitty a man of his part ſhould want, and which added to his worke, as the laudable manner is, when the authot's dead, as this man either is, or ought to be, might the gallows have its due, would much helpe to vent their thouſands:) ſo likewiſe a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient anſwer to moſt of his accuſations of value, his groſſe Lies eſpecially, legible enough in every page and paſſage almoſt of that falſe Legend.</p>
            <p>To begin then with the firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Refractori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> his <hi>Refractorineſſe.</hi> Being born to few naturall parts, and bred to leſſe learning, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wanting what might render him and his ſociety acceptable and gracefull to men of parts and worth, he betooke himſelfe upon his firſt flight from the Univerſity, to vulgar aſſociation, conſorting and keeping company and correſpondence with none, (except ſometime by intruſion) but the <hi>Ignobile mobile vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> the vulgar ſpirited rabble,<note place="margin">Charron.</note> a ſort of people naturally given to contemne their governours and ſuperiors, and to quarrell with the preſent State;
<q>(Turba gravis paci, plaoidaeque inimica quieti.)</q>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein they wanted not for that encouragement which either his doctrine or example could contribute. The particulars where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are ſo notorious with his Countrimen, as ſpecification will be needleſſe; nay I could not pleaſe him and his tribe better then to enlarge with inſtances, <hi>Irregularity</hi> and <hi>Inconformity</hi> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent government (the fruits of <hi>Refractorineſſe</hi> paſſing in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for ſuch rare vertues as they pride themſelves in nothing more in theſe times. I ſhall therefore harpe no longer on that ſtring, leſt I make him and his fellowes too much muſick, who love ſo little of what is good. Proceed we then to another: for
<q>Quiſnam hominum eſt quem tu contentum vider is uno Flagitio? —</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Impudence</hi> is his next marke.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Impudence.</note> Having a competency of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall audacity, the man hath much improved it with uſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome; having hereby arrived at ſuch an height of habituall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as he is become <hi>audax ad omne facinus.</hi> What action though of any modeſt ſober man declined comes aniſſe to him? As he is a great Athenian,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Inſtance.</note> extreamly given to heare and tell, to take in and let out news, what report favouring his party, how falſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, will not he ſpread? you ſhall have him (and 'tis his vaine from one end of the week unto the other) like the <hi>News-cryes</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:130524:7"/>London, or as it were ſome <hi>Equus meritorius,</hi> or the Cities of <hi>Veredarius,</hi> to hackney up and downe all the Towne with a piece of news that he likes, obtruding it upon his cuſtomers with that earneſtneſſe, and backing it with ſuch aſſeverations (as, <hi>beleeve it, Sir 'tis moſt true, I had it from a good hand, you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it for a certain,</hi> and the like) that it would argue want of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity at leaſt, in any that ſhould offer to diſtruſt it. When all this while, moſt an end, 'tis nothing ſo, but <hi>enjus contrarium,</hi> &amp;c. a little time having given the lye to all this confidence, and that not ſeldome, now and then by chance, but ordinarily and of courſe; whereof there is at length that notice taken by the moſt, that obſervation made of his <hi>Impudence</hi> in this kinde, that tell them but of an unlikely, improbable, unexpected, ſtrange oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, and you ſhall be anſwered ſtreightway with a Proverb: <hi>θ, this is Culmers news.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A</hi> Provtrbe.</note> Such great ſtrangers uſually are truth and his reports each to other, and ſuch a brand of Impudence hath this habit of Lying deſervedly caſt upon him. From gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, to deſcend to ſome particulars.</p>
            <p>Was it not a prerty peece of ſhameleſſe Impudence to averre (as he did) to a Committee of Parliament (when the Burgeſſes of the place were by) that the Screen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Inſtance.</note> the Partition built ath wart the Quire of Chriſt-Church, to which the Communion Table ſtands, as formerly the high Altar did, which Screen he labours to demoliſh, did joyne ſometime to (rebellious) <hi>Beckets</hi> ſhrine; and when the Burgeſſes gainſaid him, to perſiſt and ſtand in it? though himſelfe, as well as they, knew that Shrine and Screen never ſtood neare each other by divers rods.</p>
            <p>What a ſtrange peece of Impudence was that for him, firſt to report,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Inſtance.</note> as from the Committee of Parliament for Church-matters, or ſome prime member of it, that no jot of painted glaſſe muſt be left ſtanding in this Cathedrall: and when the thing was afterwards diſclaimed, as never ſaid by thoſe he vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched for it, to deny that ever he reported any ſuch thing? what playing <hi>Faſt</hi> and <hi>Looſe</hi> is here? but <hi>qui ſemel verecundiae limites tranſierit, oportet ut graviter ſit impudens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſhould he be aſhamed to charge the Quire-men (as hee doth in the petition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Inſtance.</note> a witty pithy peece of his owne noddles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention) with hudling over (what of late he loves ſo dearly) the <hi>Common Prayer?</hi> when he knowes, and ſo doe many more that he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:130524:8"/>was as guilty of the ſame himſelfe, as any Quire-man of them all. when Curate of <hi>Goodneſtone,</hi> uſing in the afternoons to be ſo quick to begin, and ſo nimble to turne over <hi>Evening prayer,</hi> upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a long way home:<note n="*" place="margin">Going ſeven nules to ſucke a Bull; a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in thoſe parts.</note> (by the way note his <hi>Non-reſidence,</hi> and his but one Sermon a day, a couple of the very neglects wherewith he taxeth the Cathedraliſts) that he had done many times before the people making to Church at two of the clocke (the accuſtomed houre) were come together, and yet threatning ſome that thereupon left his Church with the Commiſſaries Court. <hi>Turpe eſt doctori cum culpà redarguit ipſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not an impudent part in him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Inſtance.</note> to poſſeſſe the Parliament with the truth of what he hath fardell'd up in thoſe foule ſheets, ſo as to get them licenced to paſſe and come abroad by their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and under their protection: when he is conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and 'tis well enough knowne to his Countrymen, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver man abus'd the Parliament with ſuch a miſcellany, ſuch a hotchpot of falſhood, malice and ſlander, as by this paſquill he hath done? But of his printed Impudence more hereafter, when, by occaſion of his <hi>Newes,</hi> we ſhall take him to doe for his <hi>Lying.</hi> Thus then for his words, <hi>Qualis homo, talis ſermo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his Actions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Inſtance.</note> who ever put fairer then himſelfe for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vality in fame with infamous <hi>Horoſtratus</hi> (that, to get him a name, ſet fire of <hi>Dian's</hi> temple) to his ſurpaſſing Impudence in the whole acting of this Cathedralls late ſhamefull rifling, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I wis, to its through reforming? who but he had the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence to threſh and claſh downe the windows, in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous manner without any diſtinction of Kings from Saints, of military-men from martyrs, ſo contrary to his Commiſſion, the Ordinance of Parliament? for that end with an over daring boldneſſe, (by his owne confeſſion) climbing ladders of no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon height (a ſhorter one may ſerve his <hi>turne</hi> another day) no more ſcornfull then himſelfe (ſcoffing <hi>Lucianlike</hi>) in termes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Saviour, and his Apoſtles figures at their pulling downe? who forwarder then he ſhamefully to violate the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres and monuments of the dead? who ſo ready as himſelfe to flye in their faces, that expreſſed but the leaſt diſlike of his or his fellows wilde demeanour in that (for the manner at leaſt) ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and diſtaſtefull action,<note place="margin">Note.</note> yea and <hi>bloody</hi> too, witneſſe that ſad occaſion given to a poore boy to keep it in mind, by the loſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:130524:8"/>of a couple of his fingers cut quite off, by the violent throwing to of an iron doore, by ſome of the more furious inſtruments in that <hi>orderly Reformation?</hi> who but he made that place his Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, his dining roome, the place of his repaſt at that time? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſedulous, hot and intent upon the worke, that to loſe no time in following it, he tooke his bottle and bag with him to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall himſelf upon the place. If all this amount not to impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as perhaps with too many judges in theſe dayes it will not, I ſhall tell you now of Impudence with a witneſſe, and I terme it ſo, becauſe I have it from an eye-witneſſe of good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that, not without juſt ſcandall, ſaw the deed done, and will be ready, if lawfully required, to atteſt and juſtifie the report with his corporall oath.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Inſtance.</note> What doe you thinke then of piſſing in the open Church, and at noon-day, in publicke view? what the heathens of old thought of ſuch Impudence, their Poets will tell us, whereof one, thus:
<q>
                  <l>Pinge duos angues, pueri, ſacer eſt locus,<note place="margin">Perſ. ſat. 1.</note> extra</l>
                  <l>Mejite—</l>
               </q> And another, thus:
<q>
                  <l>Nec ſitis apparet cur verſus factitet,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Horace.</hi> De arte Poet. verſus finem.</note> ut cum</l>
                  <l>Minxerit in patrios cineres —</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now though we have no mention of this occurrence in his <hi>News,</hi> in the ſtory of the <hi>orderly Reformation,</hi> (ſo much of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty he hath left yet:) nevertheleſſe <hi>Ecce homo:</hi> we uſe to ſay ſometimes <hi>Mutato nomine,</hi> &amp;c. but here it needs not, for this is he, I ſay not the man, but 'tis the beaſt, the prodigy, that did the deed in the body of that Cathedrall; the firſt eſſay I thinke that ever was knowne to the converting it to (what his black mouth doth not ſticke to call it) an Augean ſtable. VVhat Chriſtians heart abominates not this unheard of, prophane, lewd impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and riſeth not in deteſtation both of it and the author? what? the Temple, Gods houſe, the place where his honour dwells, the gate of heaven, the houſe of prayer, a place to play the beaſt and piſſe in, for any, eſpecially a Miniſter? Away pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, unhallowed, impudent wretch, away I by juſt demerit, if ever any, <hi>the ſhame of the Clergy, and the ſcorne of the Laity.</hi> Nor Satyrs, nor ſcourges can ſerve, Scorpions are fitter to chaſtiſe and expiate thy prodigious impudence.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Abſciſſa viritia vellem</l>
               <l>Prodneus ſobolem ne generando parem.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:130524:9"/>
            <p> Call you this <hi>orderly reformation?</hi> Is this a peece of that reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the <hi>Abby like, corrupt and rotten condition of that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall calls for?</hi> For ſhame, beaſt, recant, repent; till when bee ſure thou gett'ſt no other eſteem with me (whiles what others thinke of thee J paſſe not for) then of a peece of obſtinate, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate, deſperate Impudence.</p>
            <p>To proceed in our charge, <hi>Covetouſneſſe</hi> is his next marke.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Covetouſnes.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Col</hi> 3.5.</note> But is he covetouſly given then? why, <hi>covetouſneſſe is the root of all evill;</hi> nay <hi>it is Idolatry.</hi> And hath the wretch beſtowed ſo much paines, ſpent ſo much time <hi>in purging away the numerous Idols, and ſweeping them out of this Cathedrall, in clenſing that Augean ſtable</hi> (tis the language of the beaſt) yet is he himſelfe an <hi>Idol-ſhepheard?</hi> VVhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt he preaches to others, is himſelfe likely to prove a caſtaway? Doth he preach downe, pull downe reputed, ſuppoſed Idols? and is he himſelfe the whileſt a reall Idolater? The <hi>Major</hi> is cleare by the Scripture, the <hi>Minor</hi> will be eaſily made good. To leave the ſtory of his griping uſury to be told by his friend, <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Piſing,</hi> and ſome others, [who can tell you of his groſſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; particularly, how that letting out money (100 <abbr>l</abbr>) upon an annuity of 10 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>per annum,</hi> for the intereſt, aſſured to him out of the debtors Lands, and that for certaine tearme of yeeres, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to take in the money, but will runne out the time.] what thinke you of him (if I may aske the queſtion) that having a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faire eſtate, a liberall fortune, being worth, ſuppoſe a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand or two thouſand pounds, or more, as ſome, to whom his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is not unknowne, avouch, which he daily improoves, by the thriftieſt, if not wretchedſt courſes he can take, and yet ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile and couſen his own ſiſters of their portions? ſhall goe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up and downe, juſt like a mendicant Friar, and pleade po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and want of meanes, [witneſſe the many viſits hee uſed to beſtow upon his poore neighbours, (when hee dwelt amongſt them) at <hi>Herbaldown,</hi> to borrow a few pence to buy himſelf and family bread, one of thoſe trickes whereby hee wound himſelfe ſo farre into the compaſſion of a neighbouring rich Matron, that in commiſeration of his hence conceived penury, ſhe made him her conſtant Almeſman while ſhe lived, and her Executor when ſhe died.] ſhall betake himſelfe to by, indirect, and unwonted, unwarranted wayes for further improvement of his fortunes, ſeeking (againſt the Law of Nature and common Humanity; for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:130524:9"/>
               <hi>Nemo debet locupletari cum aliend jacturd:</hi>) to enrich himſelfe by other mens ruines: ſhall (becauſe his deſert before theſe times could never procure him any Benefice of his owne) take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the preſent opportunities to diſpoſſeſſe another man of his, flying ſometimes at this, another while at that, and ſtill you muſt note (like his fellowes, followers of the ſame game with him) at the faireſt Livings in all the Country: You know, Sir<note place="margin">Chartham. Ick ham.</note> who is true and legall Vicar of <hi>Minſter</hi> in the Iſſe of <hi>Tanet,</hi> (a man of unqueſtionable worth in any but ſuch times as theſe, wherein the beſt accompliſhments of learning and vertue, if at leaſt rewarded upon a man by former times with any ſutable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, are all too little for his protection from ſuch envious eyes, ſnarling tongues, and undermining braines as yours, had he not all the uprighter Judges) you know, I ſay, who is Vicar there at preſent, and I know and many more with me, whoſe <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe</hi> prompts him, by malicious aſperſions and falſe ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, by indefatigable, importunate, implacable machinations, and ſolicitations againſt him, to eject and ſupplant him: wee know who's the Vicar would be. 'Tis (he ſhall be nameleſſe) <hi>Dicke Culmer, Miniſter of Gods Word, dwelling in Cantorbury, heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore of Magdalen Colledge in Cambridge, Maſter of Arts.</hi> And can you blame him? O! 'tis a benefice like the Iſland, <hi>pleaſant</hi> and <hi>fruitfull.</hi> By the way note, that 'tis the <hi>oyle of the full reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes</hi> of that Vicarage that the covets,<note place="margin">Note.</note> bearing little or no affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Flocke,</hi> but to the <hi>Fleece.</hi> And no marvell: for were the proportion of his love ſmaller, yet 'tis as much as hee's like to have returned him from thence, his good conditions being ſo well knowne, by long experience of that diſcerning people, his Countrymen (however courted of him in that <hi>Encomium</hi> both of them and their Iſland) that, not deſirous of ſuch a change, they have agreed to deprecate and obſtruct his comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, having framed a Petition to the Parliament to that purpoſe, under moſt, if not all their hands. In the interim hee ſtayes his covetous appetitc, (as well as he can) with a morſell neerer home worth ſome 120 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>per annum,</hi> or better, the Vicaredge of S. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens</hi> neere the City, whence by trickes and indirect practices, getting the proper Miniſter (onc of thoſe whom pag. 11 he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reports for <hi>Malignant Cathedral preaching,</hi> a man of choice parts, and well beloved) to be put by, he hath intruded into his place,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:130524:10"/>and thruſt in his ſickle there, though with as little ſucceſſe in point of acceptation with the people, as hee is like to finde at <hi>Minſter,</hi> if ever his project or getting thither take effect, which when it happens, wee'll all cry out with the Poet,
<q>Mopſo Niſa datur; quid non ſupremus?</q> Theſe are pretty checkes (one would thinke) to his covetous eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes, if the eyes of his minde were not obſtinately ſhut againſt them, of whoſe opening till I ſee ſome fruits, how can I chuſe, but from the premiſſes, condemne the man of <hi>Covetouſneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His next marke is <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hypocriſie.</note> whereof in a word: The diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling his eſtate by dayly pleas of poverty and want of meanes; his furious ſhewes of zeale to <hi>Babylons</hi> downefall, <hi>Babels</hi> ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction rather, his forward bold attempts for the extirpation of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and idolatry,<note place="margin">Nobilis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claeſia cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dralis <hi>Hereſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſis;</hi> nobilor <hi>Wintonienſis</hi> nobiliſſima <hi>Contuarienſis.</hi> Mat. Paris. Ann. 1254.</note> by his laying ſo much about him in the late diſanulling one of the faireſt Cathedralls of Chriſtendome; his ſeeming good affection to and compliance with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Parliamentary cauſe and wayes, his courting and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing the common peoples humour, in their late Anarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call practiſes: when all the world may ſee that all is done, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor like, meerely for private ends, and to ſerve his own turne, meerely to ingratiate and indeere himſelfe with the Parliament and people, meerely as a bait, a net layd to catch the times ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, meerely <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> as a way, a courſe that may bring him at length to that <hi>ſpirituall</hi> preferment attended with <hi>temporall</hi> profit, his ambitious covetous mind too apparantly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires unto: whence can theſe proceed but from an heart full of baſe hypocriſie? Can any tree beare ſuch fruits as that? Can you not run and read his hypocriſie?</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Clamorouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Clamorous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> beſides what arguments and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences we have of it in Print, it hath alwayes beene his vain (for want of ſome of that <hi>Comeat-Phyſicke,</hi> which pag. 23. hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes and gives to others to cure them of the <hi>clamorous evill</hi>) to mouth his owne grievances, though (for the moſt part) but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and imaginary, with ſo much uoyſe and clamour in all companies, as if his ſufferings, when eyther ſmall or none at all, (making Mountaines of Molehills) were tranſcendent beyond all paterne, above all patience, for eaſier audience and acceſſe ſake, ever pleading wife and children, and a great charge, to the conſening of many, though not over credulous, into a firm belief
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:130524:10"/>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and poore condition. Yet as clamorous as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, to others clamours none more deafe-eard then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> witneſſe (for a taſte) the dance he led a gentle woman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, comming to demand ſome dues of him, and not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be turned off with frivolous excuſes, from his Houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all the Towne, as farre as the <hi>Blean,</hi> and then (to be rid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſhewing her a payre of heeles, who would not bee ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> off untill ſhe ſaw the Fox burrowed in a thicke wood.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Et cum clamaret (quo nunc te proripis?) illae</l>
               <l>Redde, Ricarde, meam, Tu poſt virgulta latchat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But whileſt ſome are contented with this ſummary, me thinks I heare others call for a large narrative of this rare ſtory: for whoſe ſatisfaction I will over it again more punctuall and fully. A ſuit in Law then depending between our righteous <hi>Richard,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and that being,<note place="margin">The <hi>Fox</hi> hunted.</note> by conſent of both parties refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to certaine friends for arbitration, who awarded him to pay her a certain ſumme of money; the Gentlewoman, with her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his wife, comes one day to his houſe in <hi>Margarets</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, Canterbury, to make demand (in hope to receive) the a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſumme, and finding him at home, makes knowne her arrand to him. The man (like himſelfe) preſently fell to making excuſes, pretending that he was but newly returned from a journey, had ſpeedily another to take, and in the interim he was buſie at his ſtudy, being to preach the next Lords day which was at hand, and therefore he could not now intend them. But the other Gentlewoman (one of a more maſculine ſpirit then her ſiſter, and fitter therefore to encounter ſuch a baffler) well knowing the mans conditions, replied,<note place="margin">Or</note> that they had a great occaſion for the money, that he knew well enough it was their due, and he was much miſtaken if he thought they would be ſo put off; for as they came for money, ſo money they muſt have, nor would they leave him till they had it. And for his preparing to preach, it was, they knew, a meere put off, for they had not forgotten the time when he could brag what an eaſie matter it was to him to make a Sermon; he could ride and ſtudy, and was able to make a Sermon on horſe-backe; and therefore they were aſſured it was no ſuch hard matter with him now to preach, as that he ſhould offer that for an excuſe, and if that were all, he muſt not thinke they would be anſwered ſo. The man perceiving their reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:130524:11"/>not to depart without money, and being as reſolutely bent of his part to part with none, calls in all haſte to his wife for cleane band and cuffes, as if indeed he had intended a journey, which being brought him, and that not ſerving to rid them away, he takes his cloake,<note place="margin">Culmers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe,</note> and out of doores he flings, thinking to get looſe of them; but it would not be: for after their Gentleman uſher they all trudge, with repeated lewd demands of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, who regardleſſe of their cloſe purſute and clamours carries them on from ſtreet to ſtreet, meaſuring out one ſtreet after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with ſuch large ſtrides and lanching ſteps as that by what time he was gotten to VVeſtgate-ſtreet or thereabouts, Mrs. <hi>B.</hi> and her brother (a fat burley man) were ſo farre caſt behinde,<note place="margin">Or</note> and ſo outſtripp'd of their mannerly Gentleman-uſher, that they even gave out, and left him to be purſued alone by the other Gentlewoman, who indeed ſtoutly held it out, and followed him ſo cloſe, (mending her pace when he mended his) that he could hardly gaine ground of her. On then goes <hi>Dick,</hi> and up to St. <hi>Thomas</hi>-hill he makes,<note place="margin">The K— driven</note> and ſo towards Chriſt-Church wood, a good breathing you may thinke for a Gentlewoman, being nere two miles from <hi>Culmers</hi> houſe, whence they firſt fat out: whiles he leads her through the ſtreets, his pace was ſomewhat tolerable, and 'twas his wiſeſt way, for otherwiſe ſhe was reſolv'd to have made her outcries after him, that all the ſtreets might ring of the occaſion.<note place="margin">Out of Town</note> But being once gotten out of Towne, and ſo out of that danger, he made bold to runne other while, thinking ſo at laſt to caſt her off: but 'twould not ſerve his turne, for being a nimble fat woman, (it ſeems) ſhe held well with him at all paces, chattering at him all the way for the money, that all they met tooke notice of it. At length being about to take the wood, he faces about, and as once or twice before offers a parley, and asks her what ſhe meant to purſue him in that manner; ſhe gives him no other anſwer then before, that goe whither he would ſhee was reſolv'd to follow, and would never leave him till ſhe had (what ſhe came for) her ſiſters money. Finding her ſtill harping on that ſtring, and being deafe of that eare, on againe goes he, threatning to ſhew her a courſe, if ſhe would not be gone and leave him: why but (quoth ſhe) you will not, I trow, be ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill, having train'd out a Gentlewoman thus far, but you will ſee her home: whereupon he bends his courſe ſtraightway to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:130524:11"/>the houſe where he knew herſelfe and ſiſter dwelt, and when he had thus uſher'd her within or neare the ſight of the houſe, he gathers up his cloake about him, and with all the ſpeed he could, makes to the ſide of a rough thicket, hard of acceſſe, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially for a Gentlewoman encumbred with long coats, and ſilken withall, apt to be torne with buſhes and bryars, and in there he ruſhes which when ſhe perceived, bethinking herſelfe of the difficulty of a further purſuite, ſhe gives it over with this farewell to her game: <hi>Nay now I ſee the Fox is burrowed; e'ne goe thy wayes then, and be hang'd, for Ile follow thee no further.</hi> And ſo you have the ſtory.</p>
            <p>Paſſing from whence, let's have at him for his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnaturalneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Vnnatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> which indeed is ſo notorious and groſſe, as no heathen almoſt but would bluſh to be ſo juſtly taxed for the like. It is a ſaying as true as trite: <hi>Ingratum ſi dixer is omnia dixeris.</hi> Nothing can bee added to aggravate that mans crime that is once juſtly taxed of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankfulneſſe.</hi> And can any unthankfulneſſe equalize (not to dreame of tranſcending) that of a childe to a parent? and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is or can that be better tried, then when need, eſpecially if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with old age, hath rendred the unfortunate parent a fitting object of his childs reliefe? and ſuch a one is old <hi>Culmer,</hi> the Hiſtorians father, a poore aged man, and in point of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to blame in nothing more, then for too ſoon parting with what eſtate he ſometime had to this unnaturall ſome of his, who now, in requitall, ſo much neglects him (not for want of ability, but will to ſuccour him) as the whole Iland where he lives rings of the Impiety, whileſt the Monſter never ſeeks to lay the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, values it not, weighed with the ſaving of his money, being ready to take up that of the Poet:
<q>— Quid enim ſalvi infamia nummis?</q> No marvell that he proves ſuch a rebellious ſonne to the Church, his mother, that is ſo unnaturall a childe to the poore aged man, his father.</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Maliciouſneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Not to inſiſt on his continuall ſuits in Law, being indeed a notable <hi>Vitiligator, &amp; legis quam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelii peritior,</hi> a better Lawyer then Divine; I will trouble you but with one inſtance of it, which concernes a Gentleman of birth and credit, brought in queſtion for his life by the treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous malice of this grand impoſtor, who with open mouth, and all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:130524:12"/>poſſible aggravation, accuſed him to the Councell-Table of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſpeeches,<note place="margin">Recited verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim at the end of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely referred thither, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe too t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus for this place.</note> occaſioned by ſome diſcourſe betweene them about eight or nine years ſince concerning the Ship-ſeſſes and Impoſitions of thoſe times, in ſaying (as the very words of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, under his owne hand runne) that, <hi>if we have ſuch taxes laid upon us, we muſt rebell, or we muſt be faine to rebell, or to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> And the better to curry favour, and purchaſe the more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to his indictment, what ſincerity of duty doth not the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit profeſſe therein <hi>to God, and his Sovereigne Lord King Charles?</hi> for whom (ſaith he) <hi>I pray from the bottome of my heart</hi> (a hollow heart ſure,<note place="margin">Dick Culmer a Royaliſt.</note> without bottome (<hi>that the Lord would preſerve him from Dick Culmer,</hi> and his fellows, a ſort of) <hi>ſeditious and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men:</hi> with many other overtures of loyalty, ſeconded with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſame ſtamp) in a letter of his (which I have ſeen) to a noble friend of the accuſed Gentleman, written ſhortly after: wherein what profeſſions he makes of the good liking he bare to the <hi>Service book,</hi> the catechiſticall part of it eſpecially, (his ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe and care to continue conſtant to thoſe profeſſions being ſo eminent) I may not here, without wronging the man, paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in ſilence: which are theſe: <hi>Yet did I</hi> (quoth he) <hi>clearly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt my loyalty, in that I did ſo publickly take his Majeſties part,</hi> (loyall <hi>Richard</hi> I well fare thee) <hi>and in my Miniſtry I have ſhewed</hi> (full ſore,<note place="margin">An Advocate for the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</note> I doubt, againſt thy will) <hi>the like care; a ſpeciall proofe whereof I ſhewed</hi> (till thou ſaweſt thy time) <hi>in my ſhort forme of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, which I uſed many yeares</hi> (before their eyes were opened) <hi>and reſolve to uſe againe</hi> (till time beter ſerve thee to caſt it off) <hi>if it pleaſe God to reſtore mee to the exerciſe of my Miniſtery. Which forme beginneth thus: Now we have learn'd to ſay the Catechiſme, &amp;c. let us ſee more fully the meaning &amp;c. Queſt. What ſay you of our Catechiſm in the Booke of Common Prayer? Anſw.</hi> (Why, 'tis like the reſt of the Booke, <hi>Popiſh, Idolatrous, Superſtitious traſh, &amp;c.</hi> no ſtay) <hi>The Catechiſme in our Booke of Common Prayer is good, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Kings authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quanium mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus ab illo!</note> 
               <hi>and therfore we ſhould all learn it, &amp;c.</hi> (O thou limb of Antichriſt! what Prelat of them all could have ſaid more?) But <hi>ad rem.</hi> You have heard here of a heynous and capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall charge from a veſſell (of <hi>malice abſit!</hi> no) of <hi>Loyalty</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> like to produce what? but the ruine of the accuſed, by the forfeiture both of his eſtate and life. A ſad tragedy towards doubtleſſe. And yet to ſee, no ſuch matter: for <hi>auditâ alterâ parte,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:130524:12"/>when the accuſed came to his anſwer before as equall as honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Iudges, he ſo fairly and fully purged himſelfe of his foul, but falſe crimination, as brought the buſineſſe to this iſſue, that the accuſed innocent Gentleman was abſolved, diſmiſſed, whileſt his malicious unjuſt accuſer was committed, impriſoned (a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for ſuch a <hi>Perillus,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Nec enim lex juſtior ulla,</l>
                  <l>Quam necis artifices arte perire ſua.)</l>
               </q> As by the enſuing tranſcript of the Order of the Councel-board in that buſineſſe will appear to the laſting ſhame and infamy of ſuch odious malice, heightned in this,<note place="margin">A treacherous gueſt.</note> that the place where theſe pretended dangerous words were uttered, was the accuſers own table in Chriſtmaſſe time. No marvell that a Noble man, (one of the Councell-board) thereupon let fall this wiſh or deprecation rather: <hi>From ſuch gueſts good Lord deliver me!</hi> Adde hereunto that they were concealed, and not complained of, till almoſt half a yeare after, in revenge too, for the Gentlemans being (as was pretended) a means to diſpoſſeſſe his accuſer of (what he mouths ſo much by the name of his Benefice) his Curatſhip, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his complaint preferred; which 'tis knowne he loſt for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to read (what he hath ſince been heard to wiſh he had read) the booke of Liberty. But to the tranſcript taken from the very originall under ſeal. At <hi>Whitehall</hi> the 9 of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1635.</p>
            <list>
               <label>Preſent</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lo. Archbiſhop of Canterbury his Grace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lo. Keeper.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lo. Privy-ſeal.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Earle Marſhall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lo. Cottington,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mr. See. Wyndebanck.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas upon an information given by R. C. Clerk againſt E. B. of B. in the County of Kent Gent. the ſaid E. B. was ſent for by warrant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>and bound to appeare and anſwer the ſame before their Lordſhip on Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, the</hi> 9 <hi>of this preſent, this day both the ſaid parties having beene called and heard before the board: their Lordſhips finding the ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and complaint againſt Mr. B. to have been cauſleſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, did thinke fit and order, that he ſhould be forthwith diſcharged from any further attendance concerning the ſame, and that the bonds by him entred into for his appearance ſhould be delivered up unto him. Laſtly, that the ſaid R. C. ſhould, for ſuch his miſ-information and abuſe ſtand committed priſoner to the Fleet.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The 12 Tables would have condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to death:</hi> Qui falſum teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium dixiſſe convictus erit, ſaxo Tarpeio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcitor.</note> Ext. &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:130524:13"/>
            <p> And now (Reader) what thinke you of his <hi>Maliciouſnes?</hi> I conceive you expect no further evidence. Leaving that then, let's try him next for his <hi>Doltiſhnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> Doltiſhneſſe.</note> if he pleaſe, he ſhall have his booke, let him bee tried by that. VVhat judicious man having read the promiſing Title page (where he findes the author arrogating the Title and degree of a Maſter of Arts) looks over the booke, can refraine from a <hi>Scribimus indocti, doctique</hi> &amp;c. of a <hi>Parturiunt montes</hi> &amp;c. can conclude it to be other then a meere unworthy ridiculous peece, a pitifull poore, jejune, dry, dull, empty eſſay for a Maſter of Arts? Can he be thought other then a meere <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> a <hi>Duns,</hi> a <hi>Dullard,</hi> a <hi>Dolt,</hi> a <hi>Culmer</hi> that hath fardelled up a deale of bald, bold, baſe, virulent, ſcurrillous ſtuffe, as void of learning, as of truth, as void of method as full of malice, written ſurely with inke mixt and made of vinegar and kennell water,<note place="margin">A foule pen.</note> and fitter for nothing then the baſeſt of neceſſary uſes? what Maſter of Arts, but he would not be aſhamed of ſuch a blue come off? had he not great need to print his thouſands?</p>
            <q>Quid dignum tanto tulit hic promiſſor hiatu?</q>
            <p>But (here's the knack on't) 'tis fitted to the genius of (his old patrons) the vulgar, calculated to the meridian of their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and if the people, the rabble, the multitude, reliſh, taſte, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it well, quoth <hi>Dick,</hi> why <hi>Hey then up goe we.</hi> If it pleaſe their palats, and take well with them, <hi>ſatis eſt ſuper<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>;</hi> having never yet learn'd (it ſeems) that
<q>Principibus placuiſſe viris non ultima laus eſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſaith he? <hi>Equiſonem quam equitem mihi plaudere cure.</hi> Thus expects he <hi>aurum è ſtercore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> like a meere dunghill craven. But though (by his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion) 'tis ſure working by the book; yet that's not all the evidence we have to prove his Duns ſhip. Aske about in the places of his greateſt concourſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe, if you will, that beſt affect him, and you ſhall never finde their reſpect, their affection towards him grounded upon any learning or Scholler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like parts that he is guilty of. 'Tis confeſſed of all hands, that he is a very meane, dry, dull preacher, a worſe diſputant, and for the pen, <hi>fit liber Inden,</hi> I appeale to his booke. What it is that hath commended him to their affection, and begat their eſteem of him is, his forwardneſſe to heare and carry newes, and to be active and dextrous in ſuch works of orderly reformation, as that whereof he bluſheth not to make his boaſt in that Lying Legend. As for any other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter worthy of note in him, they are all as great ſtrangers to it as himſelfe. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of that.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:130524:13"/>
            <p> Now to his <hi>Lying.</hi> I have heard of a youth, one of his Tribe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>9</hi> Lying.</note> a bold, factious fellow, for Schollerſhip as errant a blockhead as himſelfe, for converſation (it may be) ſomwhat looſer, much ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed for a notorious <hi>Lyer,</hi> and ſo noted for it at the Vniverſity, that a common noted Lyer, by a new invented Proverb amongſt them, was nicknamed after him; how well he deſerved it, I partly know, but how our ſcribler, Dr. <hi>Dicke,</hi> deſerves the like, all the City, and parts adjacent, by long experience of his common, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary, habituall lying, know ſo well, that were it put to the vote there, whether or no a notorious Lyer ſhould be called a <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meriſt,</hi> I dare warrant you it would be reſolved upon the queſtion, <hi>perquàm paucis contradicentibus,</hi> in the affirmative. Whence els our common Proverb of <hi>Culmers Newes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Proverb.</note> taken up for an odious untruth, a lowd Lie? A faculty that hath ſo diſparaged his intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, whereof he makes a trade, that truth, and true intelligence fares the worſe, and wants that credit it deſerves, many times, with moſt of his good Maſters, for coming out of his mouth ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to run over with flammes and falſhoods, the juſt reward of a known convicted<note n="*" place="margin">Mendax ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lucratur, ut cùm vera di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerit, ei non credatur. <hi>Ariſt. apud Diog. l. 5</hi>
               </note> lyer. By the way, tell me, are we not like to have <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> meet apace, the hearty and unfained wiſh of all good Proteſtants, and true Patriots, whileſt theſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites mouth nothing more, meane nothing leſſe: are not theſe (I ſay) like to meet and greet apace, when, leaſt our peace ſhould returne, before their ends, their turnes are ſerv'd, to continue their diſmall diſtance, we muſt have ſuch fomenting of diviſions, ſuch flattering of parties with <hi>Lyes,</hi> lyes by the living, lyes by the dead, lyes from the Preſſe, and (would I could not ſay) lyes from the Pulpit too? But all this while we ſpeak without book: <hi>It's ſure going by the booke,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dick.</hi> Let's then from his verball, tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lies (whereof ſomwhat before in his <hi>Impudence</hi>) to his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, permanent lies: yet not all thoſe neither, for fowling too much paper, but here and there one, for a taſt and teſt of the whole pack, as we uſe to ſay, <hi>Ex pede Herculem,</hi> you may judge of <hi>Hercules</hi> dimenſions by his foot.</p>
            <p>Not to repeat that which beares the bell from all the reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Inſtance.</note> the <hi>Paſſing-bell;</hi> and to paſſe over the Petition marching in the Front, that I may not ſeem ſo raſh as to grapple with a multitude, though the thing without all queſtion be properly his own, as the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:130524:14"/>
               <hi>Amanuenſis,</hi> who lead the Petitioners into a manifeſt untruth, when he made them certifie, that Doctor <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was <hi>Parſon of Hith, Parſon of Ickham, Parſon of Well, Parſon of Salt wood,</hi> &amp;c. and Doctor <hi>&amp;c. Parſon of Back-Church in London, Parſon of Barham in Eaſt-Kent neere Dover, Parſon of Biſhopſbourne,</hi> &amp;c. when he knowes, as well as hundreds more in thoſe parts, that as <hi>Hith</hi> and <hi>Salt wood</hi> are but one and the ſame Parſonage, <hi>Ickham</hi> and <hi>Well</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſo <hi>Biſhopſbourne</hi> and <hi>Barham</hi> are no more, though he reckon the Chappells as ſeverall and diſtinct Parſonages, (one of which, <hi>Well,</hi> is long ſince deſolate) and marſhall them ſo farre aſunder, that his fallacious and unfaithfull dealing may be the better hid. To let theſe things paſſe, I ſay, and come to his Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>What an impudent lie is that,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Inſtance.</note> pag. 4. where, with ſawcie lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage towards moſt of the Bench, whom he calls <hi>malignant and Prelaticall Juſtices,</hi> he affirmes that they ſo beſtirred themſelves, that the arraigned Cathedraliſt was ('tis plaine, he means unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) acquitted? when it is notorious in the Countrey (and we have nothing but his bare word in contradiction) that the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe had a ſquare, faire triall, and the priſoner, by an whole dozen of honeſt and unbyac'd Jury-men, was legally a quitted. Thus for the text. Now what ſaith the margin? Why, <hi>A Cathedrall laſſe beguiled by a Singing-man.</hi> Like text, like margin, both falſe. The beguiler, he knowes, (nor is it unknown to Town and Countrey) was no Singing-man, but a Townſman a Chirurgion, that but a while before left the City to dwell in the Church. Now when in a thing ſo freſh in memory, he dares to falſifie ſo groſſely, what truth may we expect from his ſtories of occurrences pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to 30. or 40. years ſtanding? Withall, ſee what a tale he hath here choſen to begin with, to defile his own neſt<note n="*" place="margin">Turdus ſibi malum cacat.</note> withall, like a curſed <hi>Cham,</hi> to diſcover his fathers ſhame, by reviving the ſtory of his quondam-queſtioning for beguiling a wench, in thoſe dayes called begetting a baſtard, which otherwiſe was well nigh buried in oblivion. Doubtleſſe (friend) neither Father nor<note n="*" place="margin">Cui pater eſt populus, non habet ipſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rem.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe have reaſon to con you much thanks for this occaſion of making their credits to bleed afreſh, by ſuch unadviſed tale-telling.</p>
            <p>But ſince you will needs provoke the diſcourſe (by talking of <hi>Baſtards</hi>) prethee, man, tell me (as you are an excellent Caſuiſt)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:130524:14"/>what may be thought of their children that marty themſelves?<note place="margin">The validity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>new-faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed marriages</hi> debated.</note> (as a precious paire of your acquaintance lately did in <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi>) or of theirs either, which you and your fellowes uſe of late to couple, and put together (<hi>marrying</hi> you would have it call'd) after an upſtart, new-fangled (I ſhould ſay <hi>reformed</hi>) way of your own deviſing; with utter deteſtation, waving that of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both in point of what is to precede the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnization (publiſhing of <hi>Banes,</hi> &amp;c.) and in the ſolemnization it ſelfe (the <hi>Forme</hi> preſcribed in our Liturgy eſtabliſhed by Law.)</p>
            <p>Admit, upon occaſion, their <hi>Legitimation</hi> come in queſtion, what,<note place="margin">1 <hi>As to the</hi> Iſſues Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> I ſay, in the judgment of ſober men, regulating their opinions by the Law of the Land, may be thought thereof? or how ſhall it be juſtified? when the policie of this State hitherto (for I ſpeake not of the future, not knowing what tomorrow may bring forth) allowes not of (what their legitimation depends on) their parents intermarriage in ſuch a caſe.</p>
            <p>And doth not the like ſcruple offer it ſelfe in point of <hi>dower?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>As to the</hi> widdowes dower.</note> For, ſuppoſe that after ſuch a mock-marriage, the good-man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the widdow be put to ſue for her dower, and conſequently to plead the <hi>accouplement en loyall matrimony,</hi> I would fain know how in this caſe ſhe ſhall be able to juſtifie her plea, being married after ſuch a ſort as the Church of <hi>England</hi> (to whoſe connuſance the State transfers the plea) is ſo farre from approving, that the parties ſo coupled, in her conſtruction, (if thoſe that know her mind, I meane, Lawyers, may be credited) are ſo farre from being man and wife <hi>in foro fori,</hi> that if <hi>in foro conſcientiae</hi> they finde no tie upon them to the contrary, they may even forſake and leave each other when they pleaſe, without controll. And what fine work, my maſters, this may chance to make in time, judge ye. But by the way take this ſtory along with you, as in my judgment not impertinent, not borrowed from either <hi>Plato's</hi> Common-wealth, or Sir <hi>Tho. Mores Vtopia,</hi> but of that reality and certain truth, that 'twill be no newes at all to many now in London, ready with an <hi>Ecce</hi> (as it were) of demonſtration, to point out the parties. A watch then being lately ſet on foot between a young couple in London, and both parties and parents ſo farre agreed,<note place="margin">An inſtance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note> both in point of portion and otherwiſe, as that nothing now was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of two to make them one, but an orderly ſolemnizing their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:130524:15"/>nuptiall rites, they muſt needs, forſooth, be married (for ſo the maids father will have it) after the new faſhion, without asking, without licence, without ring, without book. The young man (for the preſent) diſſembles his diſlike of the way, and ſuffers the father herein to have his will.<note place="margin">With the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of it.</note> After this mock-marriage, what do the young paire, but, like other married couples, live and lie toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? and, by the provocation of ſuch opportunities, ſomewhat at length followed, that required the countenance of a reall marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; which the young man perceiving, and being unſatisfied both with the way of his marriage, and with the ſumme of his wives portion; or, it may be, intending to take advantage of the invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity and illegality of the one, to procure an augmentation of the other, and thinking the time now come to do the feat, what doth he, but, as if cleere of all conjugall bands, and no way obliged to nuptiall duties, forſakes his pregnant bed-fellow, diſclaims her for his wife,<note place="margin">A <hi>whore</hi> and a <hi>knave.</hi>
               </note> nay and in diſpute about the matter with her father, that he may caſt the <hi>Whore</hi> upon her, is contented to take the <hi>Knave</hi> unto himſelfe: ſo that, in ſhort, for his part, <hi>actum eſt de connu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio,</hi> hee'l no more of the match, unleſſe (for, after much adoe, to theſe termes they came at length, and this was that the young man had in project all the while) to that portion which he had had with her already, ſuch a further ſumme might be added as he required, and that they might withall be married after the old or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly manner, in the legall way of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which conditions, and not otherwiſe, he would take her for his wife againe, and uſe her as became an husband. The old ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Father-in-law finding himſelfe thus unexpectedly caught,<note place="margin">Wily beguil'd.</note> ſo much of his money gone already, and, as it proved, to no better end then to have his daughter, after ſo long proſtitution, turned back upon him with diſgrace, and all for want of a right and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly marriage pleadable in Law, thinking it his beſt way to make a vertue of neceſſity, condeſcended to theſe harſh demands, payes downe what money was required, and ſuffers a ſecond (that is, a right and orderly) ſolemnization of his daughters marriage to the ſame man, being well laughed at for his paines; and whether ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his kind or not, let any but his peeres, ſuch innovating cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combs as himſelfe, be judge.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:130524:15"/>
            <p> Another ſuch like mock-marriage there was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Inſtance.</note> happening much about the ſame time too: but the advantage here was taken on the womans part, whoſe portion being in her brothers hands, and he refuſing to part with it, unleſſe verily ſhe would take an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of his chuſing (a zealous brother, forſooth, whom ſhe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted not, being indeed in league with another man before:) ſhee cunningly diſſembles her conſent, ſo as upon the wedding-day ſhe might herſelfe receive her portion. Her brother condeſcended: ſo married they were in that ſpick and ſpan new way.<note place="margin">With its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel.</note> At night when the Bride ſhould go to bed, ſhe conditions with her Groom, that ſince they were married in a new way, ſo after a new, though preproſterous order of entring the nuptiall geniall bed, he ſhould go to bed firſt: he did ſo; then (having taken a former opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to conveigh her marriage-money into her fore-intended huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands hands) ſhe pretends an occaſion to go down, leaving the poore miſtruſtleſſe gull in bed, expecting her returne, and making ſure account to exchange a maidenhead with his Bride that night; who intending nothing leſſe, and having provided all things in a readineſſe for her eſcape, gets her away after her mony, and the next day, or ſhortly after, became his lawfull wife (by right way of marriage) whoſe ſhe was before by affection, and ſo continues, the former-mock-marriage notwithſtanding. But are we not unmannerly to leave <hi>Richard</hi> thus long? Craving then his pardon, we proceed.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Glory-cloth,</hi> whereof in the Petition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Inſtance, The <hi>Glory-Cloth</hi> vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> and againe pag. 6. to ſtop the Lyers mouth, and ſatisfie ſuch as are capable of it, ſober men, the truth of that buſineſſe is ſhortly thus: The late Dutcheſſe Dowager, of <hi>Lenox</hi> (no Papiſt, I know unleſſe her pious legary muſt make her ſo eſteem'd,) amongſt ſome other like bequeſts, conteined in her will, giving to this Cathedrall 100. pound ſterling, at ſuch time as the Society was in conſultation for repairing ſome decayes about the ornaments, and utenſills of their Church; the back-cloth upon the Screene, or Traverſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much diſcoloured, with age, and the Screene it ſelfe a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly piece of carved Tabernacle-worke,<note place="margin">The Screene,</note> which though overlaid with gold, yet when ſtripped of the imagery that ſomtime was about it, the pious and prudent (Reformers of old thought fit to be left ſtanding) in many places of it, by the golds wearing off
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:130524:16"/>being gonne alſo to ſome decay; with this 100 pound legacy, and ſomwhat added to it of their own, they purchaſed a new cloth of purple velvet, and hung it up in the roome of the other; repaired the decayes of the gold about the Screene; and for the further adorning of the cloth, and minding the beholders of the deadful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſacredneſſe of that place, not in it ſelfe, but from the high and ſacred <hi>Agends</hi> there, for the better ſeaſoning and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the approachers mindes with fitting thoughts and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their addreſſes thither (feare and reverence being to walke hand in hand with faith and repentance in that ſacramentall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) purpoſed and tooke order to have imbroydered on it in gold and ſilver, what? why even no more then is penſill'd in as glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a manner at the head of moſt Chancells in London, above the Decalogue, the glorious and dreadful name, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> with ſuitable embelliſhments. And what matter is there in all this of ſcorne, of clamour, of making the world beleeve that this <hi>Glory</hi> is their <hi>Shame?</hi> Indeed, <hi>Nunc aliud tempus, alii pro tempore mores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How falſe (next) is his relation concerning Dr. <hi>P.</hi> pag. 10. where although he have the impudence to averr that the <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall gates were ſhut a day or two for his reſcue and defence againſt the Magiſtrate and People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Inſtance.</note> &amp;c. yet in truth there was no ſuch matter; no ſhutting of gates, but in the night time, as at other times before and ſince, till they were heav'd off and laid by. Nor did the party ever hide himſelfe, or was concealed by the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dralliſts, as he pretends, but when demanded by the City-Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, preſently yeelded himſelf without the leaſt reſiſtance, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word or deed, as many both of the Church and City of more credit then Dr. <hi>Dick,</hi> can, and, if required, are ready to atteſt.</p>
            <p>To let paſſe his Lie of the <hi>Mutiny</hi> at Canterbury,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Inſtance.</note> recorded pag. 12. a thing that never was above ground; ſee how he faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and falſifies in his Winters-tale concerning the fall of the Vane and Pinnacle, pag. 13. going about to perſwade ſtrangers (he cannot thoſe that live upon the place, and know the contrary, &amp; ſo dare tel him to his face) that the Vane with the Archb. Arms pulling down the Pinnacle which upheld it, in the fall was carried <hi>(partly againſt the winde) a good diſtance from the ſteeple, and fell upon the roof of the Cloyſter, in which Cloyſter the Armes of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:130524:16"/>Archbiſhoprick of Canterbury were carved and painted on the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſide or concave of the arch or ſeeling of the Cloyſter; which Arms in the Cloyſter were daſhed in pieces by the Armes which fell from the Pinnacle of the ſteeple. The Armes of the preſent Archbiſhop</hi> (ſo he ſummes it up) <hi>brake down the Armes of the Archbiſhoprick or Sea of Canterbury:</hi> adding in the next page, that the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall-men repairing the broken Cloyſter, gilded and painted the arch over head as it was before: <hi>but</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they have made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Coat-Armes in the roome of the Arms of the Archbiſhopricke, becauſe they would conceale the ſtrange ruine of thoſe Armes. Mendax lingua quò vadis?</hi> for here is lie upon lie, one in the neck of another, <hi>ſic unda ſupervenit undam,</hi> and thoſe, for a taſt of his Poeticall learning, ſummed up in the cloſe with certain capring times, to give his Readers palate ſome variety, or rather for the lies better authorizing: for <hi>Pictoribus atque Poetis, &amp;c.</hi> what Priviledges Poets and Painters have in this kinde, is notorious. Would you know the truth? Then thus it was. About the time he ſpeaks of,<note place="margin">Truth cleered concerning the <hi>Vanes.</hi>
               </note> ſuch Vanes were indeed erected for the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and accommodation as well of ſtrangers travelling by thoſe parts, as of the Inhabitants upon and neere the place; the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminent place of their choſen poſiture, yeelding great advantage for a vaſt latitude of publike aſpect. Of theſe ('tis true) that with the Archbiſhops Armes upon it, in that great ſtorme on S. <hi>Johns</hi> night, 1639. fell, and in the fall drew down with it the top of the pinnacle whereon it ſtood: but that the Pinnacle and it were carried any diſtance from the ſteeple, with the wind, much leſſe againſt it, is moſt falſe; ſince who yet obſerves may ſee, they fell directly downe into that corner of the Cloyſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath, almoſt contiguous to the very pillar of the ſteeple which ſupports both Pinnacle and Vane.</p>
            <p>What he adds (that in their fall, they bare or brake down the Armes of the Archbiſhoprick carved and painted on the lower ſide or concave of the arch, or feeling of the Cloyſter &amp;c.) is a lie as notorious as the former, there never being any Armes of the Archbiſhoprick either carved or painted in the place of the breach; nay no Armes at all, but ſuch ordinary worke as in the reſt of the untouched roofe on all parts thereabouts is at this day to bee ſeene. 'Tis true there was on the one hand of the breach, the Arms
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:130524:17"/>of the noble houſe of <hi>Arundell</hi> quartered with another coate, as there was of ſome other (or a plaine ſhield rather) on the other ſide, and thoſe are ſtanding ſtill, undemoliſhed by the fall: but for other Armes there or thereabouts, of the Archbiſhoprick eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, though magiſteriall <hi>Richards</hi> own ſelfe averr it, yet (if<note n="*" place="margin">Cuilibet in ſua arte, perito eſſe credendum</note> Heralds and others may be credited to whom the Cloyſter with the Armes about it, by curious and frequent obſervation ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of both, before this breach was made, was and is better knowne then ever to him, or any of his tribe) he lies as groſſely, as the man you wote of that told us of the miraculous ringing of the Archbiſhops paſſing-bell, or as he that talks of eating a Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſet out of the Cathedrall baſon, p. 20. or as he (the very ſame hand guided both pens) that ſaid, the Miniſter that ſucceeded M. <hi>Culmer.</hi> upon his ſuſpenſion, for refuſing to read the booke of <hi>Liberty.</hi> ſhortly after drown'd himſelfe. Nor doth he otherwiſe when he aſſignes the reaſon for taking downe all the other three Vanes, to be Cathedralliſts policie, <hi>for taking away the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and remembrance of that downfall, which concerned their graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Dioceſan, and great Cathedrall ſo much.</hi> Whereas the known and onely cauſe hereof was, an experience by this unhappy acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, of the weakneſſe and inability of the ſlender pinnacles to ſupport them in ſtormy weather, without indangering the ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: a thing, from the very firſt, ſo much feared of the moſt of the Churchmen, that, but for the forwardneſſe of ſome one or two, (whereof the one in Office for that yeere, who afterwards ſmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſuch his forwardneſſe, being at his paſſing his accompts, made to pay ſome part of the charge out of his own purſe, as I have heard) they had never been ſet up; ſo ſtrong was the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition againſt it from the reſt of the company.</p>
            <p>Where he inſinuates (pag. 18.) that none but <hi>Proctors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Inſtance.</note> 
               <hi>Fidlers, Tapſters, and other friends of the Cathedrall and Prelaticall party at Canterbury, were for the Archbiſhops Secretary to be Burgeſſe there</hi> &amp;c. how ſawcy and falſe too is hee in that aſſertion? when 'tis knowne, nay the fellow knowes it himſelfe, that the then Mayor, all the Aldermen, but one, moſt of the Common Counſell, beſides divers prime Citizens and Freemen, that were neither <hi>Proctors, Fidlers,</hi> nor <hi>Tapſters</hi> &amp;c. gave, or were ready to have given their voices for the Gentlemans election. By the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:130524:17"/>way, friend, how rude and uncivill (not unlike your ſelfe in this ſawcy terme reflecting, if you marke it, upon no ſmall number of your good Maſters) the oppoſite partie was in that action, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me to the indifferent and ſober partie of that aſſembly.</p>
            <p>As for his aſſertion and triumph, in that abſurd compariſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Inſtance.</note> pag. 24. <hi>That now there is no ſuch heterodox malignant Cathedrall ſtuffe heard at Chriſt-Church, as before this bleſſed Reformation, &amp;c.</hi> What he meanes by ſuch epitheted ſtuffe I know not. But 'tis too well knowne to Town and Country, that ſince this <hi>bleſſed Reformation,</hi> ſince the ſetling this <hi>able and orthodox Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> as he calls it, ſince theſe young beardleſſe boyes came thither to preach <hi>in Quirpo,</hi> ſince this change of <hi>Aenea pro aureis, of Droſſe for Gold,</hi> there hath beene and is ſuch ſtrange matter deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered there for <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſuch upſtart new-fangled ſtuffe for <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> as ſtartles many ſober, orthodox,<note place="margin">New <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> new.</note> well-affected Chriſtians to heare, One cries down the <hi>Liturgy</hi> (the Service-Book eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Act of Parliament) with ſtale, thred-bare, long ſince refuted, exploded arguments, pick'd from the ſcurrilous, libellous papers of <hi>Martin Marprelate, T. C.</hi> and their fellowes. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther labours to diſaffect his Auditors to it, with odious compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons betwixt it and <hi>conceived</hi> prayer, reſembling that to the conſtant and unvaried note of the <hi>Cuckow;</hi> this this to the ſweet and changeable tunes of the<note n="*" place="margin">The ſame mouth was ſince that, out of another Pulpit, heard to wiſh, that all thoſe that bowed at the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> might be crooked, and that as many as kneeled at receiving the Communion, might riſe up no more, or to that effect.</note> 
               <hi>Nightinghale.</hi> One (and more then one, and with more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary violence too, and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the ſpirit of contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the orthodox Doctors and Doctrine of our owne and all other reformed Churches:) will have no Communions at all, fiercely condemning it both in the giver and receiver, becauſe, forſooth, of the mixture of good and bad, the precious with the vile, at thoſe meetings; Anabaptiſtically fancying to themſelves, and no leſſe parado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xically, a CHVRCH here upon earth <hi>without ſpot or</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:130524:18"/>
               <note n="†" place="margin">And is not here brave ſport for the <hi>Romaniſts?</hi> we that were wont to upbraid them with their halfe Communions, are now come to fall ſhort of that, and deny all. Beſides, what's become of that <hi>Note</hi> which wee aſſume of a true Church <hi>(the right Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments)</hi> when we will adminiſter none at all?</note> 
               <hi>blemiſh.</hi> Another will have no <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> no forme of Church-government, but that wilde one of <hi>Independency,</hi> proteſting, and declaming againſt all other formes as repugnant to holy Scripture. Thus they preach, and will you heare now a little of their <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tickets come to them from this and that good Siſter thicke and three-fold,<note place="margin">And <hi>Praying.</hi>
               </note> one muſt bee (and was) remembred and commended in a thanksgiving to Almighty God for <hi>an overflowing meaſure of the spirit in her,</hi> (to the admiration you may thinke of all her Goſſips.) Another muſt have, and had, their prayers for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>her lack and want of the ſpirit,</hi> (to your Siſter, Goſſip, and ſhare with her of her <hi>Overflowings.</hi>) A third, whereof I ſaw and read the Ticket, ſo ill written, both for authography and ſence, as I never ſaw any thing of that kind more ridiculous and abſurd, muſt have, and had, their thanks and prayers too for a brother of hers: <hi>Thanks</hi> to God, for the opening of his eyes, and bringing him to the ſight of his error; and what was that? why, taking up Armes, and ingaging his perſon as a Souldier on the Kings par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: <hi>Prayers,</hi> for what? why, that he ſhut not his eyes againe, and having deſerted the King,<note place="margin">A <hi>holy ſiſter</hi> beguiled.</note> revolt, and relapſe into his former error, Another of the Siſterhood, a ſedulous and noted frequenter of their zealous exerciſe, both publike and private, having caught a clap of late, beſides the prayers made in her behalfe, both here and elſewhere, how did one of theſe <hi>Orthodox</hi> Miniſters, tooth and naile, <hi>omni cum valido ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> beſtir himſelf in a Sermon the next Lords daie, made on purpoſe to ſalve the matter, and reconcile her to the offended Congregation, from that proper and pertinent Text of Scripture, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 1. whileſt ſome of the Siſterhood, hearing how the tongues of certaine of their owne tribe were la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh in the cenſure of their collapſed Siſter, and in ſuch termes too as tended to the diſcredit of their righteous profeſſion, tender of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:130524:18"/>the conſequence, laboured to diſſwade them from ſuch ſcandalous cenſures, condiſcending to have her called <hi>Whore,</hi> but not,<note place="margin">Cenſured.</note> as ſome would terme her, <hi>Round-head-Whore.</hi> And is not the world well mended, my Maſters, at Chriſt-Church, <hi>ſince this able and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Miniſtry was ſetled there?</hi> doth not the Hiſtorian juſtlie, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie celebrate this alteration? A remedie indeed as bad, if not worſe then the diſeaſe, not through the Phyſitians fault though, but theirs rather, who like pragmaticall patients, will take no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke but of their owne preſcribing, admit of no Paſtors but of their owne recommending; a miſchief which the wiſdome of our State hath ever laboured to prevent, by oppoſing popular Votes in the election of Miniſters, which cure, if at this day for a while remitted, will, I doubt not, be re-aſſum'd againe, after ſome few ſuch miſcarriages as this, have ſufficiently informed the world of the inconvenience, <hi>Fiat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have you heard of ſome of the Hiſtorians good qualities,<note place="margin">Peroratio.</note> to which I might juſtly add more, ſuch as his <hi>Arrogance, Envy, Revenge, Rudeneſſe:</hi> but ſince they are glanced at before, and you may nauſeate what you have already, ſuch unſavoury ſtuffe it is, and chiefly leaſt ſome over-curious Anagrammatiſt ſhould pleaſe himſelfe too much with picking out his name <hi>(Richard Culmer)</hi> from the firſt letter of each word in this goodly Poeſie put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which, to avoid the giving ſuch a hint, I have <hi>ex profeſſo,</hi> and of purpoſe, marſhalled otherwiſe then they lie in the mans name, and that ſomewhat may be reſerved for a ſecond edition, if he ſhould provoke it, by obtruding his <hi>Newes</hi> upon us a ſecond time, I will ſtop here, neither fowling my own fingers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draliſts accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency <hi>debated.</hi>
               </note> nor blaſting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eares with repreſenting any more of his wretched conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at preſent. And by this time, Readers, you may be ready, I ſuppoſe, for a queſtion, and be ask'd what you think of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of the Cathedraliſts Accuſer, now that you have ſeene him unmas'd? Is not <hi>Dick Culmer</hi> a fitting man to accuſe other men, and in that bitter, ſatyricall, ſarcaſticall phariſaicall way too,<note place="margin">Quis tulerit Gracchum?</note> that is ſo many wayes obnoxious to juſt reproofe himſelfe? to record, to make a Regiſter of Cathedrall evills, of Cathedraliſts vices, that is ſo great a ſtranger to all vertue himſelfe? Were it not a great deale fitter, while the hypocrite is pulling <hi>Motes</hi> out of his brothers eyes, or pulling out their eyes rather, if that will
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:130524:19"/>content him, for 'tis their extirpation onely, not reformation will ſerve his turne, that he were caſting <hi>Beames</hi> out of his owne? Was there ſo little choice, that a more righteous man then he could not be found, on whom to lay the Province? In reaſon ſuch a Cenſor ſhould himſelfe be <hi>rectus in curia,</hi> nay <hi>integer vitae, ſceleriſque purus,</hi> ſome <hi>Cato,</hi> or an <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> a man of exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry juſtice, and morall integrity. It was indeed the ſaying of as honeſt a man ſomtime as himſelfe:<note place="margin">Machiavel.</note> 
               <hi>Accuſa fortiter, haerebit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid.</hi> Accuſe home be ſure, and doubtleſſe thou ſhalt not loſe thy labour. But then, as generally in caſes of this nature, the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ought himſelfe to be <hi>integrae famae,</hi> a man without exception. Shall a <hi>Jew</hi> accuſe a <hi>Jew? Claudius</hi> cannot paſſe for a competent accuſer of a <hi>Moechus,</hi> nor <hi>Catiline</hi> of <hi>Cethegus.</hi> Amongſt the liſt of juſt exceptions by the Civill Law ſerving to repell an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, I have met with theſe: 1. <hi>Infamie,</hi> 2. <hi>Capitall Enmity,</hi> 3. <hi>Guiltineſſe of the ſame crime,</hi> and 4. <hi>Sacriledge.</hi> To all which exception and many more, how liable our precious Recorder is, <hi>ex allegatis &amp; probatis,</hi> is ſo notorious, as that henceforth (after this Antidote I meane) I ſhall not doubt to find both the Accuſer and his Accuſation (the <hi>Newes</hi> and the <hi>Newes-monger</hi>) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly eſteemed with indifferent Judges.</p>
            <p>As for the Proctors booke,<note place="margin">The <hi>Proctors book</hi> vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> about which he keeps ſo great a ſtir, (I pray tell him) had he thought me worthy of one of his books, (as well as ſome others that I thinke had as little relation to him) I ſhould have thought my ſelf more obliged to have ſaid ſomwhat in his defence, however for the booke it ſelf, I will ſay ſo much for truths ſake, that I have heard many whom I tooke to be judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious men, and well-affected to the Publike, ſpeake of it with good reſpect: but to this day never heard any (of any judgement) blemiſh it with any ſuch imputation laid upon it, as that of <hi>much advancing Idolatry,</hi> (pag. 22.) But may he not be thought his owne foe in flying ſo eagerly and angrily into the face of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor?</hi> For (if it be true that I have heard) that he hath the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Neck-verſe Booke</hi>) time may come, when the <hi>Proctor</hi> may doe him a ſpeciall courteſie. Friends, you may one day be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to him, (ſince you talke of Bookes) for that booke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (if it be not above your learning, being written in Latine) to prevent an aſcent upon the fatall Ladder, which your readineſſe to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:130524:19"/>come up the firſt, and your feats upon it, may ſooner bring you then you are yet aware of. A rope was then as a bridle about your loynes, take heed it get not up higher and prove hereafter a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar for your neck. <hi>Dick!</hi> you bad the Prelate remember the Pina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, but me thinks I heare ſombodie make you this returne: <hi>Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer! remember you went beyond your Commiſſion:</hi> And indeed,<note place="margin">A <hi>jeer</hi> retorted</note> (friend <hi>Richard</hi>) as much as you joy and ſcoffe at the hearing of the Cathedrall-Gates, looke it come not to that paſſe one day, that you wiſh the <hi>City-Gates,</hi> nay the <hi>Kingdomes-Gates,</hi> (the Ports ſtood as wide open as theſe, when one paire of heeles may be worth two paire of hands, when an eſcape away may prove your beſt ſanctuary againſt ſuch a legall triall by the knowne Laws of the Land, as may turne you over to <hi>Tiburne-Faire.</hi> And then <hi>Bones Noches, good night Dick.</hi> In the meane time, <hi>Clama, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, exclama uſque ad Ravim—Rumpantur ut Ilia.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Barke, bellow, bawll; do even thy worſt,</l>
               <l>Till both thy bowells and thy belly burſt.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:130524:20"/>
            <head>A Copie of the Information preſented to the Councell-Table by <hi>Richard Culmer,</hi> againſt M. <hi>E. B.</hi> whereof mention is made before, Parag. Maliciouſneſſe, Numb. <hi>7.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Heard M. <hi>E. B.</hi> of <hi>B.</hi> in the pariſh of <hi>G.</hi> next <hi>W.</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Ship-taxes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Culmers</hi> firſt charge againſt M. <hi>B.</hi> for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt the <hi>Ship-Seſſes.</hi>
               </note> ſay, that ſuch and ſuch places were taxed ſo much, and ſome ſo much &amp;c. and in the end he ſaid, that if we have ſuch taxes laid upon us wee muſt rebell, or we muſt be faine to rebell, or to this effect punctually, and hearing him ſay ſo, I ſaid, that if we conſidered our burthen with others compared, we had no cauſe to thinke of Rebellion. The next occaſion I could finde I called him aſide after <hi>Evenning-ſong,</hi> and gave him the beſt admonition I could, telling him, that I could not heare ſuch words but with deteſtation, and ſaid, that as a Subject, and a Miniſter, and a Gueſt, I was bound to tell him what I did, and intreated him for the Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, that he would forbeare ſuch ſpeeches, elſe I would never come to his houſe more, with other ſpeeches to this effect. He replied, did I ſay ſo? yes ſaid I, that I did heare you ſay; aske your wife and friends at home. After that he never ſpake word of it more, till, I heard of late, he in a paſſion againſt me, at ſome meeting, railing upon me, hoping to get my<note n="*" place="margin">Your <hi>Curat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> good <hi>Richard!</hi>
               </note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice for his Coſin <hi>H.</hi> by my<note n="*" place="margin">The very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rade you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rive your ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this day.</note> ruine, he there, as I heard by credible Information, amongſt other vile compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſpeeches againſt me, ſaid, that he invited me to his houſe at Chriſtmas, and afterwards I called him aſide, and would have him accuſe himſelfe, but he ſpake words of ſedition, when as I did it not to bring him into a ſnare;
<pb facs="tcp:130524:20"/>If I had, I would have called witneſſe, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhed him, but the Lord knoweth I did it out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> duty to God and my Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Charles,</hi> for whom I pray from the bottome of my heart, that the Lord would preſerve him from ſeditious, and rebellious men. And my wife ſaith, ſhee well remembreth the ſame ſpeech of his and mine at the Table.</p>
            <p>And I heard the ſaid M. <hi>B.</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">His ſecond charge againſt him, in behalfe of the Booke of Sports.</note> having read over the booke of <hi>Sabbath-Recreations,</hi> and delivering it to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Evenſong in the Church, I asked him if he had read it, he replied, yes, it will make a good privy ſeale. And my wife and I heard him in our own houſe ſay of the ſaid booke, that it was, as if a Schoolmaſter ſhould ſay: it is a good boy, ply thy book and thou ſhalt go to play in the afternoone. And I and my ſervant heard him ſay, that it was unfit ſuch bookes ſhould be ſent for Miniſters to read in the Church: yet after he had a project to get my Benefice, he to collogue for it, ſaid in my hearing that it was a good booke, and if it were read the Sabbath would be better kept then ever it was. Dated July the 31. 1635.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Per me Rich. Culmer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
